{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>Buckley v. Valeo</em> used this amendment to overturn the Federal Election Campaign Act.<em> Chaplinksky</em> <em>v. New Hampshire</em> unanimously declared that \u201cfighting words\u201d did not apply under this amendment. The Supreme Court\u2019s requirement that \u201cactual malice\u201d be involved in libelous pieces was the basis for their ruling in<em> New York Times v. Sullivan</em>. For ten points, name this U.S. Constitutional amendment that protects free speech and free press.", "answer": "<b> 1</b>st Amendment", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For many years, Ohio Congressman Ralph Regula blocked attempts to rename this landmark, which is normally climbed by the West Buttress Route. Gold prospector William Dickey coined a name for this peak; in 2015, that name was officially replaced by its local Athabascan name, translating to \u201cthe high one.\u201d For ten points, name this highest peak in North America, an Alaska mountain that was previously named Mount McKinley.", "answer": "<b> Denali</b> (accept Mount<b> McKinley</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The Fuller Syndicate invested in these systems as part of the Gould system. The Gadsden Purchase was completed to obtain good land for one these systems. Acts passed in 1862 and 1863 created land grants and set a uniform gauge for these systems, one of which was finished at Promontory, Utah with a golden spike. The Union Pacific and Central Pacific collaborated on the first of, for ten points, what 19th century construction projects that allowed quick transport across the U.S.?", "answer": "<b> transcontinental railroad</b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Bill Gates distributed pages of this man\u2019s Codex Leicester [lester] as a Windows screen saver. This man wrote in reverse cursive in notebooks detailing water-walking shoes and an early helicopter design, and he superimposed two images of a man inscribed in a circle and square in his<em> Vitruvian Man</em> drawing. For ten points, name this Italian Renaissance scientist and artist, whose non-journal works include the <em>Mona Lisa</em>.", "answer": "<b> Leonardo da Vinci</b> (accept either underlined name)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Hans Blix led a 2002 commission that investigated this country\u2019s weapons development program; it found no evidence of weapons of mass destruction, contradicting George W. Bush\u2019s claims. For ten points, name this Middle Eastern country where, in 2003, a US-led coalition invaded and deposed its leader, Saddam Hussein.", "answer": "<b> Iraq</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this work, the fourth ditch of the Malebolge [mall-uh-bowlj] is home to sorcerers who walk with their heads turned backwards. This poem\u2019s narrator avoids a leopard, a lion, and a wolf by passing through a doorway that warns, \u201cabandon all hope, ye who enter here,\u201d and later discovers the traitors Cassius, Brutus, and Judas writhing in the mouths of Lucifer. The poet Virgil guides the narrator during, for ten points, what first section of Dante\u2019s<em> Divine Comedy</em>, in which the author explores the circles of Hell?", "answer": "<b> Inferno</b> (prompt on Divine Comedy before mentioned)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "A group that performed this action in 19th century New York, called the \u201cBig Six,\u201d used a symbolic Bengal tiger that was adopted by Boss Tweed. Marcus Licinius Crassus led a Roman group that refused to perform this action if the customers refused to pay, after which he often purchased the ruins. In Philadelphia, Ben Franklin organized a \u201cbucket brigade\u201d to perform this action. For ten points, name this public service provided by professional groups like the FDNY in New York, which protect structures from combustive destruction.", "answer": "<b> firefighting</b> (accept clear equivalents; prompt on broader descriptions, like \u201cemergency services\u201d or \u201cfirst responders;\u201d do not accept police or medical occupations)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this war, murderous<em> mitrailleuse</em> [mih-tray-uhs] and Chassepot [shass-poh] fire stalled one side\u2019s attacks at the Battle of Gravelotte. After this war, Baden, W\u00a8urtemburg, and Bavaria joined a country that also gained Alsace-Lorraine through the Treaty of Frankfurt. This war ended shortly after the losing leader was captured at the Battle of Sedan. For ten points, name this war in which Napoleon III was soundly defeated by a state led by Otto von Bismarck.", "answer": "<b> Franco-Prussian</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This composer wrote a piece for the funeral of the Electress of Saxony Christiane Eberhardine known as the<em> Trauerode</em>. He wrote a piece to cure Count Kaiserling\u2019s insomnia; that piece consists of an aria and thirty variations and was twice recorded by Glenn Gould. A collection of preludes and fugues in every major and minor key was composed by, for ten points, what Baroque composer of the<em> Goldberg Variations</em> and the<em> Well-Tempered Clavier</em>?", "answer": "Johann Sebastian<b> Bach</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This case\u2019s plaintiff tried to have the verdict overturned in<em> McCorvey v. Hill</em>. This case, which was decided alongside<em> Doe v. Bolton</em>, inspired the introduction of the Hyde Amendment. This case balanced a right granted by the Due Process Clause against other state interests by restricting a certain action to the first two trimesters. For ten points, name this 1973 case that legalized abortion in the United States.", "answer": "<b> Roe</b> v. Wade", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This company ran the ad campaign \u201cLike a Rock.\u201d The Black Keys named their second album for a product by this company, which is namedropped in the chorus of Don McLean\u2019s \u201cAmerican Pie.\u201d Jimmie Johnson\u2019s #48 car in NASCAR was made by this company, which survived the 2009 bankruptcy of its parent company with the introduction of a hybrid model, the Volt. For ten points, name this division of General Motors that produces the Silverado, Camaro, and Corvette models.", "answer": "<b> Chevrolet</b> (or<b> Chevy</b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This character\u2019s elder brother was killed by Spaniards in the 1658 Battle of Dunkirk. This character escapes capture by Sallee pirates with the slave boy Xury, and he watches his friend tease and kill a bear before being surrounded by 300 wolves. This character is surprised by the discovery of a single footprint on the beach of an island he calls \u201cDespair.\u201d Alexander Selkirk is thought to have inspired, for ten points, what castaway who titles a novel by Daniel Defoe?", "answer": "<b> Robinson Crusoe</b> (accept either or both names)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "These devices were used in \u201c596,\u201d an event at Lop Nur. The Dimona Institute in the Negev is widely suspected to be used for manufacturing these devices, which South Africa no longer possesses. \u201cSmiling Buddha\u201d was the codename for India\u2019s proof of possession of these devices. A \u201ctriad\u201d of submarines, aircraft, and ballistic missiles are used to deploy, for ten points, what weapons that have not been used in war since 1945, when Harry Truman ordered their use against Japan?", "answer": "<b> nuclear</b> weapons (accept equivalents like<b> atom bomb</b>s,<b> hydrogen bomb</b>s, etc.)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s Syracuse Speech prompted angry protesters to set the slave William Henry free. His popularity plummeted after he declared himself not as a \u201cNorthern man but as</b> <b>an American\u201d in his (+)</b> <b>Seventh of March Speech. He declared \u201cLiberty and union, now</b> <b>and forever, one and inseparable\u201d in a debate with Robert (*)</b> Hayne, and he helped resolve the Aroostook War with the Baron Ashburton. For ten points, name this Massachusetts senator who formed the Great Triumvirate with Henry Clay and John C. Calhoun.", "answer": "Daniel<b> Webster</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A mould found in Trend, Jutland was used in the tenth century to cast both crosses and this pagan icon. This mythological item failed repeatedly to kill Skr\u00b4ymir, and it was created</b> <b>along with (+)</b> <b>Gullinbursti and Draupnir by Sindri and Brokkr, a pair of dwarves. This</b> <b>Gullinbursti and Draupnir by Sindri and Brokkr, a pair of dwarves. This</b> <b>object was wielded with J\u00b4arngreipr, a special (*)</b> <b>object was wielded with J\u00b4arngreipr, a special (*)</b> glove to which it would always return when thrown. Loki\u2019s interference caused this weapon\u2019s deformation, a short handle. For ten points, name this mythological hammer used by Thor.", "answer": "<b> Mj\u00a8ollnir</b> [m\u2019yoll-neer] (prompt on Thor\u2019s hammer\u201d until mentioned)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Theodor Benfey proposed a spiral replacement for this construct. This construct gained</b> <b>popularity because its developer left empty spaces for (+)</b> <b>predicted, missing members,</b> <b>which were given prefixes like</b><em><b> eka-</b></em><b>. Synthesis work by Glenn Seaborg led to a 1945 expansion of this construct, adding a row for (*)</b> actinides. This construct is organized in an 18-column array, progressing by atomic number. For ten points, name this construct developed by Dmitri Mendeleyev that groups all of the known chemical elements.", "answer": "<b> periodic table</b> of the elements", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One structure on this island was built slightly north of the Stanegate and was near the</b> <b>Military Way. Julius Caesar made note of the (+)</b> <b>chariots used on this island during his</b> <b>55 BC invasion. Gaius Suetonius won the Battle of Watling Street on this island to defeat a revolt of the Iceni led by (*)</b> Boudicca. One structure on this island was built near Pictland as the northern border of the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this island, the site of Hadrian\u2019s Wall and a Roman province with capital at Londinium, now known as London.", "answer": "<b> Britannia</b> (or<b> Britain</b> or the<b> British</b> Isles)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>On this island, Koxinga founded the Kingdom of Tungning after driving off the Dutch</b> <b>from Fort Zeelandia. This island was ceded by the Treaty of (+)</b> <b>Shimonoseki to Japan.</b> <b>This island was an alternate target for the American invasion of the Philippines during World War II. (*) </b> Chiang Kai-Shek and the Kuomintang fled to this island after the Chinese Civil War. For ten points, name this island, once known as Formosa and currently home to the Republic of China, whose capital is Taipei.", "answer": "<b> Taiwan</b> (or<b> Formosa</b> before mentioned) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>This country fought the Soviet Union in the Battle of Khalkhin Gol and used</b> <b>its Kwantung Army to annex Manchuria. It used prisoners of war to build the</b> <b>Burma Railway, as depicted in (+)</b><em><b> The Bridge on the River Kwai</b></em><b>, and this country</b> <b>committed atrocities like the Rape of Nanking and the (*)</b> Bataan Death March under Prime Minister Hideki Tojo. For ten points, name this country whose surrender to the Allies ended the Pacific theater of World War II. ANSWER: Empire of<b> Japan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}